(Transcribed by TurboScribe. Go Unlimited to remove this message.) Ladies and gentlemen, please welcome Vice President of
Engineering, Vic Gundotra.
Well, good morning, everyone.
Welcome to day two of Google I-O.
I hope you all had a great time
yesterday.
I hope you enjoyed your sessions, and I
hope you enjoyed those Android phones.
Yesterday, we promised you a surprise for this
morning.
And this morning, Google will surprise you.
We are about to unveil a personal communication
and collaboration tool in a very early form.
We decided to do this at this forum
for a couple of reasons.
This unbelievable product, one that I'm very, very
excited about, will be open sourced.
It's open sourced for many reasons.
Not only do we want to contribute to
the internet, but frankly, we need developers to
help us complete this product, and we need
your support.
So we hope after you see this, you're
as excited about it as we are.
And number two, we decided to unveil this
product in its early form at this conference
because it is an unbelievable, powerful demonstration of
what is possible in the browser.
I guarantee you that over the next hour
and a half as you see this product,
you will forget that you are looking at
the browser.
And I want you to repeat after me,
I am looking at an HTML5 app.
I am looking at what's possible in the
browser.
And I hope you are as excited and
delighted as I was when I first saw
the thinking behind this product.
Now, it shouldn't surprise me that this product
would be magical.
After all, the engineering leadership had already produced
a magical product.
The engineering leadership behind what you're about to
see is the work of two brothers and
an amazing engineering team with them.
Those two brothers are Lars and Jens Rasmussen.
You might remember those names because those were
the same amazing people that did another magical
app called Maps, Google Maps.
And so you'll see what they've been working
on unveiled for the first time today.
So why don't we go ahead and get
started.
Remember, this is an early developer preview for
this audience.
Everyone in this room will get accounts to
give us feedback.
And we'll talk about that a little bit
later We have your email addresses, so you
will get those passwords a little bit later
on, likely tomorrow.
With that, let me just go ahead and
get started.
Let me introduce Lars Rasmussen and Stephanie Hannon.
Thank you very much.
I shall wake up my laptop.
Good morning, everyone.
Thank you very much for coming early.
I know you've been here partying all night.
We're going to show a demo today of
a product that we've been working on for
a couple of years down in Sydney, Australia.
It's called Google Wave.
And it's a communication and collaborations tool that
we're launching later in the year.
Like Vic said, it's a little unusual for
us to be showing it to the world
this early.
The reason we're doing it is very simple.
We're starting a developer preview today.
You guys will all get accounts on a
sandbox build of the system.
You're the first outside of Google to see
this.
And you'll be the first to get accounts
on the system.
And we're doing that because, as you'll see
from the demo, Google Wave comes with a
set of really nice APIs.
And we're hoping we can persuade you guys
to start building cool things with those APIs
while we're getting the product ready for launch,
which is going to happen later this year.
Because that way, when we do launch, our
users and your users can enjoy both Google
Waves and all the cool things that we
hope you'll build at the same time.
Let me introduce Stephanie Hannan.
She's quite possibly the best PM in the
world.
Good morning, I.O. Thank you, Vic, for
the invitation to be here.
We couldn't imagine a better audience to show
our product to first.
I second that.
Our presentation today is in three parts.
First, we're going to show you a demo
of the product.
Second, we'll show you the APIs that Lars
talked about.
You can use Waves to enhance your website.
And you can build extensions to Wave itself.
Third, we'll show you that Wave is also
a protocol.
We are very passionate about this being an
open system of communication.
We hope other people build Wave services that
interoperate with ours so users have choice in
their provider.
We affectionately call this the three Ps, product,
platform, protocol.
And we'll talk about them all today.
OK, so communication.
Email today is by far the most popular
way for us to communicate on the internet,
which is remarkable.
Because email was invented more than 40 years
ago, before the internet, before the web.
And it was done without the experience of
things like SMS, and instant messaging, and blogs,
and wikis, and bulletin boards, and discussion groups,
and social networks, and wikis, and media sharing
sites, and collaborative editors.
All of these different kinds of communication that
we take for granted today.
Also, of course, computers and networks have dramatically
improved in those four decades.
And so when we started this project, and
it's been more than two years, we asked
ourselves the question, what might email look like
if it was invented today?
And needless to say, there's about a million
different ways you can answer that question.
What you're going to see today, Google Wave,
is our attempt.
And so let me start by briefly contrasting
email from Wave.
Email essentially mimics snail mail.
The basic metaphor is you write a message,
and you send it to one or more
recipients.
And then email systems, and we like to
think Gmail does this particularly well, can collate
related messages into conversations or threads.
Wave, by contrast, starts out with the definition
of a conversation, which is simply a lightweight
tree structure of messages and a set of
users participating in that conversation.
And then instead of thinking of individual messages
as being sent back and forth, we think
of the entire conversation object as being a
shared object hosted on a server somewhere.
And users that participate can open up that
Wave, leave their replies, go away.
And then when the next user comes, she
can open up that same shared object, see
those replies, and add her own.
That's how the Wave grows.
That's how the conversation builds up.
And you'll recognize that this is a model
akin to how bulletin boards work.
We found that with a tight enough implementation,
you can use that to build a single
communication tool that has functionality spanning quite a
lot further than what you can do with
email today.
And so we'll show you a demo.
It'll take you through a series of usage
scenarios that you'll be familiar with, but where
today we would use different tools for each
one.
We'll show you how it all fits neatly
in this one metaphor of hosted conversations.
So what you are looking at is an
HTML5 app that we built with a Google
Web Toolkit.
On the left side is Lars running Chrome.
On the right side, I'm running Safari.
And a little bit later, we're going to
throw in Firefox.
So the same thing is being shown on
each pair of screens.
You can just choose one to look at.
OK, so we'll start with plain vanilla email
-type conversations, and we'll show you how it
looks in Wave.
We're planning a boat trip, and I'm going
to start by clicking new Wave here, and
then I'll type my title in the first
line.
Watch your spelling, Lars.
There's a lot of people.
There is a lot of people.
They can't see what I'm typing anyway.
Are you ready for the boat trip?
Hey, Steph, did you guys like the spell
checker?
Thank you.
We'll talk more about that later.
Since you don't want to watch me type
for an hour, we put canned messages in
there.
We'll try hard to pull them out before
we launch.
I click done.
It asks me for more users.
I'll add Stephanie.
And since she is offline, I'm going to
go stare at a blank page.
So I will open Wave, and you'll see
in my search panel, the middle panel, there'll
be an unread message from Lars.
He's asking me if I want to go
shopping before this boat trip, so I'll do
something very email-like, which is hit reply
and say, I love shopping.
I wrote the script.
I need new fins.
Let's go.
The first benefit I want to show you
of this being a hosted conversation is it's
easier to keep track of structure.
If this was email and I wanted to
reply to the middle part of Lars' message,
where he asked which bus to take, I
would hit reply.
The email client would copy the message, and
I'd hand edit in the response.
Because this is a hosted conversation and it
lives in one place, I can just instruct
the server to split the message apart and
say, you never wake up early.
Which is true.
Let's take the late bus.
Okay, Lars isn't online.
I'm going to close this Wave.
So a little bit later, I come back
online, and you'll see, for starters, that that
Wave is now bold to show me there's
new material in it.
When I open it up, Stephanie's first message
gets the highlight, and I can navigate the
conversation with my keyboard and, of course, continue
her thread here.
You know me too well, like that.
And that's how plain vanilla email-type conversations
work in Wave.
So you've noticed that we have carefully avoided
having the Wave open on both screens.
When we do have the Wave open at
the same time, my message bounces right off
the server into Stephanie's browser.
And the effect is that you can also
do instant messaging-type conversations in Wave.
In fact, in the same Wave, you can
switch back and forth between these different ways
of communicating.
I'll show you that now.
Shiny.
You must know a good store.
There is a new one over on George
Street.
Cool.
Let's go at seven.
Sounds good.
Let's invite Jens, too.
Okay.
So you notice that we didn't wait for
me to hit done before showing Stephanie the
message, but rather, and this was difficult to
do, we transmit live almost character by character
what I'm typing.
Why did we do that?
It's because with today's instant messaging tools, you
spend half of your time looking at it,
saying, Stephanie is typing, she's typing, she's typing,
she's typing, and then you see what she
said.
Thank you.
But because, in general, you can start formulating
your own reply before Stephanie is done typing
hers.
By doing this live transmission, you end up
spending 100% of your time either reading
or writing, which dramatically speeds up the conversation.
Now, needless to say, there are times you
don't want everyone to see every keystroke, in
particular if you spell like I do, and
so we have this checkbox here.
All you have to do is check it,
and now no one can see what you're
typing until you hit that done button.
This is one of the features we haven't
implemented quite yet.
Okay, and so that's how email conversations, or
rather email-type conversations and instant messaging-type
conversations no longer require two separate tools.
Next thing we want to show you is
how easy it is to add a new
person to an ongoing conversation.
Can I just introduce my brother, Jens, by
the way?
Give him a hand, please.
So we want to add Jens to the
conversation.
If this was email, I would take the
last message here, reply to it, and add
Jens to the recipient list.
There's two problems with that.
For starters, because we branched the conversation up
here, that last email message would not contain
the entire conversation, but also, if Stephanie then
later, when it replied to an earlier message
of mine, Jens wouldn't get that anyway.
You end up with these cat-and-mouse
games.
In the Wave model, all you have to
do is make Jens a participant in the
Wave like that, and now I'll switch over
to Firefox here, where Jens has already signed
in.
So now that I'm on the Wave, I'm
going to open it, and, of course, everything
is going to be marked as unread for
me.
But because I was added late, I didn't
get to see Lars' message in one piece,
and by the time I'm added, they could
be arbitrarily far apart.
So we added a feature called Playback.
So I get to see Lars' original message,
Lars asks Stephanie, Stephanie replies, Stephanie does an
inline reply, and so on and so on.
Thank you.
So Playback turns out to be a really
useful feature, particularly when a Wave starts picking
up more structure, and we'll show you more
of that later.
But now that I've caught up on this
Wave, I'm going to just add my reply.
Me too.
Oh, I think I crashed.
Did I mention that it's a developer preview?
So we made sure to inject a few
bugs so that you wouldn't have too high
expectations.
I'm just kidding.
Yeah.
Did you notice how quickly it reloads?
Did we mention we used GWT?
All right, so I'm going to add my
reply.
Me too.
Don't forget your keys.
And then I'll hand it back to Lars.
Thank you.
So that's how easy it is to add
a new person to an ongoing conversation.
And so often we end up having very
nice group conversations in Wave, and then occasionally
you want to say something in a Wave
that's not visible to you.
We call that a private reply, and I'll
add one down here at the bottom, and
I'll say, let's buy Steph a really nice
present.
I wrote this part.
And then I will add just Jens, and
you will see if I just quickly flip
over to Jens' browser and scroll down, he
sees that private reply, but if you look
at Stephanie's screen, she doesn't see it.
If you remember, I've explained that a Wave
is a tree structure of messages.
Essentially, you can take any sub-tree of
the Wave and restrict access to a subset
of the participants.
Okay, I switch back to my own account
here.
The next thing we want to show you
is how attachments work in Wave.
So we've been on a boat trip.
It was very nice.
Thank you.
And we all got pictures.
I have six of them sitting here on
my desktop, and I'm going to drag them
onto the Wave like this.
You might not have
noticed, but the thumbnails appeared on my screen
long before the full images were uploaded from
Lars' computer.
I'll show you that again by dragging in
my own photos from iPhoto.
Ready?
Here we go.
I can see them show up over on
my screen.
Don't be shy, you guys.
If you like what you see, don't be
shy letting us know.
We can handle pretty much any amount of
applause.
This feature, drag and drop from the desktop
to the browser, is the one part of
Wave that HTML5 can't support yet.
We're working on a proposal to add it
to the standard.
In the meantime, you need to download gears
for this specific feature to work.
It's the only part of Wave that you
need gears for.
When Lars dropped in his images, you might
have noticed at the bottom of the Wave
panel, there's an image menu with actions you'd
probably do on images like upload or download.
What's important is these actions apply to all
the images in the Wave, not just the
ones I dropped in, which makes Wave a
really easy, lightweight way to create a group
photo album together, which is surprisingly hard to
do with today's tools.
Here's the photo album.
This is Captain Athena.
Here's the hard life down under.
As advertised, you'll see over here Stephanie's images
show up in my slideshow so that I
can show you just how much fun life
down under is.
And that's images.
So that's how easy it is to share
photos in Wave.
This was a group trip.
We'll all throw our photos in here.
We'd probably share it with the rest of
the office to make them envious.
In this particular case, it's not clear that
we want everyone to know that we went
shopping together, and so one of the features
down here lets me copy just the images
from this Wave into a fresh Wave.
Boating in January.
Enjoy all.
Here and yonder.
And then I'll add Stephanie to this.
I can now share that with the rest
of the office.
Now, this feature here of extracting images from
a Wave and putting them in a new
one is actually part of a very important
design principle for us, namely that we care
just as much about the product of a
Wave that we do the Wave itself.
And we'll show you more examples of that
later.
Yes, we will.
I forgot what's next.
How about we show them the embedding APIs?
Excellent idea.
Okay, thank you.
So...
She's right.
We should have rehearsed this before coming this
morning.
Just kidding.
So the first category of APIs that we
want to show you are APIs that let
you embed Waves onto your web pages.
It's very similar to the Maps API, which,
by the way, thank you, everyone who used
it.
We consider your enthusiasm for that API an
enormous factor in that product's success, and we're
hoping, obviously, to repeat that with Wave.
Give a round of applause to themselves.
Oh, yeah, a round of applause to yourself.
Well done.
Okay, so here's an example application.
It's a little blogging site we've built.
It's over on Google App Engine, but you
could build it anywhere you host your website.
And this blogging site, in addition to embedding
Waves on its pages, it provides me with
this robotic participant that we affectionately call Bloggy.
All I have to do is add Bloggy
to the Wave, and now you'll see, you
can probably not read that, but on that
yellow banner, all users on the Wave is
now warned that Bloggy, this new participant, has
published the blog on a page which we
built over in App Engine.
Can I just introduce Gregory Dallasander?
He's another PM on the team.
And he's gonna show you the blog site
now.
Hi, I'm Greg, and I'm a huge fan
of Lars' blog, just like everybody on the
team is told they should be.
I'm gonna show you...
He makes us read it.
It's a good blog.
Come on.
Hold on just a second.
Did we lose?
Did we lose VPN?
Yes, I think we might have.
Lars, this is where you do the dance.
Oh, yeah, I dance.
Everyone look at me.
Don't look at the screen.
Dun-dun-dun.
The Wave.
Dance.
I think we lost all the...
Neener-neener.
There's not a...
And then...
There's not a lot of people in the
world that can have their demos as spectacularly
fail in front of 4,000 people and
not break a sweat.
It wasn't the demo.
We wish we were one of them.
I think your proxy server might be missing.
Oh, there we go.
All right, we're back.
So, as I was saying, the blog.
So in the blog, one of the cool
things you can see is that we're not
just embedding the images.
We're actually embedding the whole Wave with all
of its UI.
This means that I can respond, hey, that
looks fun.
Why wasn't I invited?
The same way we embed...
And we do...
You can respond the same way you do
in the Wave client.
Exactly.
And so now I can see, obviously, Greg's
question from inside my Wave client.
I can answer it from in here.
I don't have to go to the blog
site to do that.
I could if I wanted to, but I
can say here, um, I lost the phone
with your number.
I really, truly can't spell.
Here we go.
So one of the things you just saw
is that I happened to be online when
Lars was online, and I saw his response
coming in live on his blog.
That's not always gonna be the case.
Since I responded to this blog, it'll show
up in my Wave client right after I
refresh my Wave client.
Um, it will show up in my Wave
client, and I can continue the conversation in
there.
But Lars, I live next door.
And, um, and then we can, that response
shows up on the blog.
We can continue the conversation from there, and
anyone else can join in that conversation.
Thank you, Greg.
Thank you.
And so this, again, is an example of
how to use our embedding APIs to put
blogs on your Web pages.
And here we showed you with a blogging
site, but you could imagine discussion group sites,
community forums.
If you have a rich media site, you
can let your users discuss that using Waves.
The benefit for developers, of course, is you
get to provide this very live, rich experience
with very little code.
For your users, for starters, they get to
use a familiar UI, but for those of
your users that have Wave accounts, they get
to walk around the Web and aggregate the
conversations they're interested in into the Wave client
so that they don't have to go check
back on 10,000 different pages whether someone
responded to them, which will make Flame Wars
so much more effective.
She hates that joke.
I hate it.
Okay, so that was an example of how
to embed Waves.
The embedding APIs can do other things, and
Stephanie will show you that now.
So we invited some of our colleagues from
Brazil and India to Sydney who work on
one of our social networks called Orkut.
We wanted to build a demo of what
it could look like to put Waves inside
of Orkut.
Obviously, it's a place where lots of discussions
happen.
It demonstrates three important principles or features of
our embed API.
Let me load up the demo.
So here's my Orkut account, and you can
see there's a Wave panel in the middle,
and the first thing is I can create
a Wave on Orkut.
So I'm starting a new Wave, and I'll
say Brazil trip.
Wonder when Lars will let me go.
The second important feature is that you can
use contacts other than your Wave contacts.
In this case, the authors of the site
chose to use the Orkut contacts, so I
can add some of my Orkut friends like
Sid, Torsten, and Rodrigo, who all helped build
this demo.
The third principle is that I can embed
a search panel inside of Orkut using the
embed API.
I'll show you that now.
I can search for all my Waves from
Yun and so on and look at them.
So that's Waves embedded in Orkut.
What's important is that our embed API is
powerful enough for you to build your own
Wave client.
In this case, the Orkut team chose to
focus on Waves created inside of Orkut, but
just like in the blog example, I can
go back to my Wave client, and I
can see the Wave I started there.
Wonder when Lars will let me go to
Brazil.
So that's the embed API.
You guys...
Thank you.
Are you guys feeling inspired yet?
So remember that we're all gonna give you
accounts on a sandbox build, which is, in
fact, the build that we're demoing from later
today, and this is all sample applications that
we're hoping you'll pick up and build much,
much cooler things with.
Okay, so the next thing I want to
show is, of course, you're going to want
Waves on your mobile devices, and I have
an Android and an iPhone here, and I
was gonna show you how well it works
communicating from mobile devices to the desktop, but
you guys are all on Facebook, aren't you?
Because I can't get on the wireless.
So if it doesn't work, it's your fault.
Okay, so you can see my inbox over
here.
This is on the Android device.
Here's an open...
the same open Wave we saw before.
You see the pretty pictures here, and then
I can click the reply button like this,
and you'll see over on Stephanie's screen, which
I can't see, you will see a reply.
Imagine I was actually on a network, and
then I could type in, I am on
the boat.
Done.
Notice again my spelling, and nothing is gonna
show up over there because we haven't yet
figured out squeezing this through without a connection.
Maybe we'll show you that.
As long as it's your fault that it's
not working.
I just don't want to screw up.
We are working on it.
Okay, so that's mobile.
How about we talk about editing?
Oh, that's a brilliant idea.
Thank you.
Okay, so the next thing I want to
show you, again, because there's only...
back to my desktop, thank you.
There's only one copy of the Wave out
there.
Even though we put these pictures on my
blog, I discussed them with Greg, we had
them on my mobile device, now I notice
that some of the captions are kind of
wonky, and all I have to do is
click this edit button here, and then I
can fix that.
Kayaks, beer man, and thank you.
And as you notice, the captions are updating
on the blog.
Yes, hopefully you saw that the captions were
actually updating live on the blog as I
was typing.
So here I edited my own message, but
we actually let users edit each other's messages
as well, which has a very nice effect
that in addition to everything we showed you
already, you can use Waves to collaboratively author
documents, which we'll show you now.
So let's leave the boat behind, and let's
go to work.
As Lars mentioned, I'm a product manager, and
I often have to take notes in a
meeting.
Today I have to decide if I want
to send those notes out on email because
I want people to discuss them, or if
I'm going to put them in a doc
or a wiki because I want other people
to help me edit them.
With Wave, you don't have to make that
choice.
You can do both discussion and content collaboration
in one tool.
So these are our meeting notes.
I'm going to add Lars, Jens, Greg, and
ACD.
And now I open it.
Then you open it.
Then I open it.
And even though this is Stephanie's message, I
can click that same edit button and change
this to glorious, and then I can add
an action item.
AI, make more better AIs already.
Ooh, like that.
Thank you.
And so that's how easy it is for
me to edit Stephanie's message.
We want to show you now how it
looks to the other participants on the Wave,
the fact that I edited her message.
We'll start with Stephanie.
So you can see the Wave pop back
into my inbox because there's new material.
If I open it, I see the markups.
So I see the changes that Lars made.
Thank you.
We haven't implemented it yet, but we also
have a little description at the top that
says Lars edited this message.
What's important is I see these markups not
because I wrote the original message but because
I saw the original message.
Anyone who saw my original message would see
these same markups the next time they visited
the Wave after Lars made his edits.
Now, I didn't get to see the original
message, so when I open up this Wave,
I just see the current version of it,
but I do get to see that both
Stephanie and Lars wrote this message.
Most of the time, I'm not going to
care, but if I do care, then playback
is my friend again.
So I see Stephanie's original message, she adds
Lars, and then I get to see Lars's
edits.
Thank you.